<?xml version="1.0"?>
<eml:eml packageId="david_remsen.20.1" system="knb" xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
 <dataset> <title>The Paleobiology Database Checklist of Species</title>
 <creator id="1267121131015"> <individualName><givenName>John</givenName>
<surName>Alroy</surName>
</individualName>
<electronicMailAddress>alroy@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://paleodb.org</onlineUrl>
</creator>
 <associatedParty id="1264777976227"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
<givenName>David</givenName>
<surName>Remsen</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>GBIF Secretariat</organizationName>
<positionName>Programme Officer</positionName>
<address><deliveryPoint>GBIF Secretariat</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>Universitetsparken 15</deliveryPoint>
<city>Copenhagen</city>
<administrativeArea>&#216;</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>2100</postalCode>
<country>DK</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">+45 28751472</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>dremsen@gbif.org</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.gbif.org</onlineUrl>
<role>Metadata Provider</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>{pubDate}</pubDate>
<language>en</language>
<abstract><para>The Paleobiology Database is a public resource for the global scientific community. It has been organized and operated by a multi-disciplinary, multi-institutional, international group of paleobiological researchers. Its purpose is to provide global, collection-based occurrence and taxonomic data for marine and terrestrial animals and plants of any geological age, as well as web-based software for statistical analysis of the data. The project's wider, long-term goal is to encourage collaborative efforts to answer large-scale paleobiological questions by developing a useful database infrastructure and bringing together large data sets.

Taxonomic data is derived fro the PBDB data downloads page.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>fossil</keyword>
<keyword>dinosaurs</keyword>
<keyword>extinct</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights><para>Data is in the public domain if it is accessible via the download site

We encourage making all contributed data publicly accessible. However, all faunal and floral data sets entered into our system may be protected so that they are not viewable either by any other users (your private data) or by anyone outside of your research group (your group data). Protection is limited for up to two years after date of entry for previously published data, and up to five years for unpublished data. Your own password will allow you to view research group-readable data belonging to any group that includes you. Protected data cannot be accessed by any of our scripts or in any other way unless the appropriate password is provided. The only exceptions are the reference search and taxonomy scripts, which need to access all the reference and taxonomy data because there is little subjective interpretation and we need to avoid duplicate entry of published data.</para>
</intellectualRights>
<contact><references>1267121131015</references>
</contact>
</dataset>

<additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
		<recordLinkUrl></recordLinkUrl>
		<logoUrl></logoUrl>
    </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>

 </eml:eml>

